Records of the Office of Institutional Research and Planning 1959-1975 RG.6.3
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of Institutional Research and Planning
1959-1975, 2017-ongoing
New York University Archives
New York University. Office of Institutional Research and Educational Planning
RG.6.3
2.5 Linear Feet (6 manuscript boxes)
3 websites in 3 archived websites.
The Records of the Office of Institutional Research and Planning contains published survey studies, notes, summaries and memos produced between 1959 and 1975. These include materials on New York University's academic programming, faculty, facilities and students. This collection also contains the website for the Factbook, which is made up of statistics on personnel for New York University dating back to 2008. The Factbook is managed by the Office of Institutional Research and Data Integrity.
Conditions Governing Access
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job searches and all files included in the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are also restricted. For information on specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
http://www.nyu.edu/employees/resources-and-services/administrative-services/institutional-research/factbook.html was selected by University Archives curators in 2017 through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In February 2023, https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/external.reporting/viz/Factbook_15680534792720/Enrollment/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.016. In December 2024, https://www.nyu.edu/employees/resources-and-services/administrative-services/institutional-research/self-service-reporting-resources/undergraduate--graduation-and-retention-data1.html and https://www.nyu.edu/employees/resources-and-services/administrative-services/institutional-research/self-service-reporting-resources/factbook.html were added. The accession number associated with these websites are 2025.001.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Arrangement
The material in this collection is arranged chronologically in two series.
History of the Office of Institutional Research and Planning
NYU's Office of Institutional Research and Planning (sometimes referred to as The Office of Institutional Research and Educational Planning) was created in Spring 1953 as the office responsible for carrying out the University's self-study. The office was under the supervision of the University's Executive Vice Chancellor, who headed the office for the first few months before Associate Dean of the School of Law Miguel de Capriles was appointed director.
In 1961 NYU's Board of Trustees approved the merger of the Office of Institutional Research and Planning with the Office of the Coordinator of Research Services to create the Office of Research Services, under the umbrella of the Academic Affairs Office. It is unclear exactly when the transition of authority over this office occurred.
In 1971 the Office of Research Services became the Office of Sponsored Programs. That year the Academic Affairs Office also changed names, becoming the Office of Academic Development. These offices retain these names at this writing.
The Factbook is managed by the Office of Institutional Research and Data Integrity, which aims to "guide the university's academic, administrative and operational units for effective university planning and progress through analysis, consistent information dissemination, decision support and technical data expertise." The office is part of NYU's Human Resources' Administrative Services.
Related Archival Materials
See RG 15.5 Records of the New York University Self-Study.
See RG 9.5 Records of the Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs, Leslie Berlowitz.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of reports on NYU's degree programs, faculty, scholarship programs, applicants, facilities, financial aid and administrative policies published between 1959 and 1975. Preliminary reports and summaries are also included. It contains some correspondence and supplementary material such as memos, newsletters and brochures that pertain to reports or studies in the collection.
There are several reports on student progress in the Martin Luther King, Jr. Scholarship Program, started in 1969, as well as reports on students who declined the offer of admission to NYU or left to attend other schools. Attention is also given to transfer students and foreign students.
The Office of Institutional Research and Planning also conducted surveys and studies of faculty morale on topics including university policies, procedures, salary and students.
Memorandums.; Reports.; Notes.; Correspondence.; African American college students; Brochures.; Newsletters.; School personnel management.; College students -- New York (N.Y.); Statistics.; New York University. University Heights; New York University. College of Arts and Science; New York University. Martin Luther King, Jr. Scholarship Program; New York University -- Buildings; New York University -- Administration -- 20th century; New York University -- Students
- Series I: Reports and Subject Files, 1959-1975
  - Correspondence-- Re: Study of Faculty Satisfactions and Dissatisfactions, 1959-1963, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Recent Trends in Numbers of Degrees Granted at NYU, 1959 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Instructional Programs of New York University: Academic Year 1957-1958, 1959 February (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Instructional Programs of New York University: Academic Year 1959-1960, 1961 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Condensed Summary of Preliminary Report on Study of Faculty Satisfactions and Dissatisfactions, 1961 August (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Preliminary Report on Study of Non-Immigrant Foreign Students at NYU, 1961 October (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Informal Comments on the Faculty Questionnaire; Frederick L. Redefer, 1961 December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Satisfactions and Dissatisfactions: A Methodological Study of Part II of the Russell Questionnaire, 1962 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A Study of Faculty Opinions and Attitudes at Fordham University, 1962 May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Graduate Programs at New York University--Memoranda, 1963 March (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Report of Commission on Coordinated Liberal Studies, 1963 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Salaries-- Reports. Memoranda, Newsletters, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Report on Freshman Candidates Who Declined Offer of Admission, 1964 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Report on Freshmen Candidates Who Declined Offer of Admission, 1965 June (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Placement Services-- Memoranda, Brochures, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Report on Committee to Review the All-University Department Concept, 1968 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda-- Re: Study of Engineering Degree Programs Relating to Determination of the Teaching Cost of Producing a Graduate, 1968 July (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Some Characteristics of Doctoral Degree Recipients 1967-1968, 1968 December (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Student Services and Activities-- Reports, Memoranda, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - First Year Performance at NYU of Transfer Students from Junior Colleges, 1969 January (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Per Student Cost Comparisons, SUNY and NYU; 1962-1963, 1967-1968, 1969 January (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tuition Remission Policies for Staff Members, 1969 February (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Utilization of Classrooms at University Heights-- Fall 1968, 1969 February (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Martin Luther King Freshmen: Report on Academic Performance Progress and Ongoing Support Programs, 1969 March (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Freshmen in the Martin Luther King, Jr. Scholarship Program: A Report on the First Semester, 1969 April (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The University and Its Programs for the Afro-American: A Progress Report for the Academic Year 1968-1969, 1969 April (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Problem Areas of Martin Luther King, Jr. Scholarship Students, 1969 May (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Utilization of Classrooms at Washington Square Fall 1968, 1969 May (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Freshmen in the Martin Luther King, Jr. Scholarship Program: A Report on the First Semester, 1969 May (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Loeb Student Center Annual Report, 1968-1969: A Decade of Service; 1959-1969, 1969 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Report on Freshmen Candidates Who Declined Offer of Admissions; 1959-1969, 1969 September (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Quality of Classrooms at Washington Square, Fall 1969, 1970 January (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Report on Gould Student Center, 1970 January (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Washington Square Journal: An Assessment, 1970 January (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Classroom Space, Washington Square Center, 1970 March (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Quality of Classrooms at University Heights, Spring 1970, 1970 April (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Report on Freshmen Candidates Who Declined Offer of Admissions, 1970, 1970 June (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Report: Areas Needing Standardization, 1970 August (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Report: Subcommittee B of the Committee on Standardization of Student Records, 1971 February (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Proposed Revision to Course File Creation and Course File Maintenance Registration Subsystem, 1971 March (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Proposed Revision to Student Program Change Procedures, 1971 March (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Student Record Keeping System, 1971 March (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and Tables Regarding Freshmen Retention and Attrition, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Martin Luther King, Jr. Grant Program After Two Years, 1971 May (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Problem Areas of Students Admitted as Freshmen in September of 1968, 1971 May (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Report on Freshmen Candidates Who Declined Offer of Admissions, 1971, 1971 September (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Financial Aid Survey, 1971-1972, 1971 November (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Why Freshmen Leave New York University and Where They Go, 1972 March (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and Tables Regarding Freshmen Retention and Attrition, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Graduation Rates of Students Admitted as Freshmen in 1968, 1972 November (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Financial Aid-- Its Effects on Enrollment, 1973 January (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Financial Aid Survey, 1972-1973, 1973 January (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Recruiting Report: Fall 1971, Spring 1972, Fall 1972, 1973 January (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Report on Admissions: The September 1972 Class, 1973 February (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Admission Statistics and Recruitmen Activities Fall 1973, 1973 March (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Undergraduate Enrollment at NYU: A Review of the Past Ten Years, 1973 April (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Report on Freshmen Who Declined Offer of Admission, 1973, 1973 September (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Assumptions Regarding the Environment for Higher Education in New York City in 1981, 1973 October (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Level of Education Necessary for the B.A. Degree in 1981, 1973 October (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Survey of Recent Graduate Alumni of New York University, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Why Graduate Students Came to New York University, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Why Prospective Graduate Students Reject New York University, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Early Admission Students, Fall 1972, 1973 December (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Financial Aid Survey 1973-1974, 1973 December (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Some Ideas to Improve the Financial Prospects for the University, 1973 December (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Effect of Job Market Demand on Future Enrollment, 1974 January (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Financial Aid: Its Effects on Enrollment, 1974 January (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Interim Report/1981 Goals Committee Report, 1974 January (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1972 Master Plan Progress Report, 1974 January (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Policy Implications of "The Assumptions Regarding the Environment for Higher Education in 1981", 1974 February (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Preliminary Report: Graduation Rate of Students Admitted as Freshmen in 1969, 1974 February (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Consolidation of Classroom Usage, 1974 March (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Graduation Rate of Freshmen in 1968 by Geographic Area, 1974 March (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Projections of Enrollment and Income for 1974-1975 to 1976-1977, 1974 March (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Projects for Institutional Research, 1974 March (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Financial Aid: Its Effects on Enrollment, 1974 April (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Why Freshmen Left New York University and Where They Went, 1974 May (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Freshmen Receiving Financial Aid, 1974 June (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Projections of Point Production for 1974/1975-1976/1977 and Demand for Additional Faculty, 1974 July (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Graduation Rates of Undergraduate Students Who Entered NYU as Freshmen, 1974 September (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Why Undergraduates Transfer to New York University, 1974 September (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - A Study of Fall Day Freshmen Candidates Who Declined Offer of Admission to New York University, 1974 November (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - A Composite Report on Existing Information on Attrition and Retention of Undergraduates at New York University, 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Financial Aid Survey, 1974-1975, 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Fall 1974 Day Freshmen Candidates Who Declined Offer of Admissions to New York University, 1975 January (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Profile of New York University Students, 1975 January (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Report on Admissions: The September 1974 Class, 1975 January (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - A Study of Non-Returning Students Who has Pre-Registered in Washington Square and University College for the Fall Semester of 1974, 1975 January (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - A Comparison of Degree Productivity at New York University with Degree Productivity in New York State, 1969-1970 through 1972-1973, 1975 January (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - NYU Bachelor Degree Graduates from 1971 & 1973: A Survey, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Undergraduate Commuter at New York University: A Survey, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Report on the Rate of Graduation of Day Freshmen Who Entered New York University in Fall of 1963, 1965, 1967 and 1969, 1975 May (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Report on the Survey of Undergraduate Students Who Transferred to New York University in February 1975, 1975 June (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Persistence and Attrition Among Undergraduate Day Students Who Tranferred to New York University in Fall of 1971, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1975 Fall Day Freshmen at New York University: A Survey of Their Expectations and Experiences, 1976 January (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - A Study of Faculty Satisfactions and Dissatisfactions at New York University, 1960-1980 (Box 7, Box 8)
- Series II: Archived Websites, 2017-ongoing; 3 websites in 3 archived websites.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the website for the Factbook, which is made up of statistics on personnel for New York University dating back to 2008. Since 2015, the university used Tableau, a visualization software, to display statistics and also compiled statistics in PDF form. The statistics document enrollment and admission rates, enrollment by race and sex, graduation and rentention rates, financial aid, faculty and staff statistics by race and sex, and tuition.
  Appraisal
  Crawls were expanded to include PDFs and Tableau. The public link to the Tableau table was added to the web archives to attempt to achieve a more navigable crawl but was not added to the finding aid.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Tableau graph is inconsistently captured.
  Accruals
  Websites accrued annually.